it would really be nice to have a doover
if our habits or our genes have led us
to develop plaque in Our arteries I
suppose it doesn't need much explanation
but having less space in your arteries
because you have a cholesterol packed
plaque cutting into your blood
circulation is a recipe for disaster
from stroke to heart attack and more so
is it then possible for something like
exercise which we know benefits our
health to give us that doover by erasing
the plaque found in Our
arteries ultimately what we care about
is avoiding the outcome of death and
just before that cardiovascular events
like stroke heart attacks and so on
fascinatingly exercise can help prevent
that from happening through more than
just removing plaque from Our arteries
according to this scientific review the
researchers acknowledged that exercise
can reduce plaque in Our arteries but
how exactly well plaque formation is a
culmination of multiple factors coming
together to allow for an atheroma that's
the plaque to build in brief your blood
vessel wall has these proteins under an
initial layer of cells called
endothelial cells these proteins called
proteoglycans attract a type of particle
called an APO containing lipoprotein
these lipoproteins bind to the
proteoglycans and can be oxidized or
modified in doing so this leads to a
Cascade of events from immune cells
invading the area to the formation of
necrotic core which involves the death
of immune cells under the endothelial
layer and as this continues to progress
the aoma grows ultimately it pushes into
the open area of the blood vessel where
blood flow is supposed to be occurring
called the Lumen this is important
because if the lumen complet completely
closes there's no more blood flow that
goes Downstream to the rest of the body
that means a lack of nutrients oxygen
clearing on metabolites and more this is
called an
occlusion we'll return to some more
specifics on all that because there's
something unique that exercise does to
that atheroma aside from shrinking it
but how does a trinket at least
mechanistically remember when we briefly
discussed the immune Sy cells invading
the forming atheroma to deal with the
stuck lipoproteins well they invade
under the endothelial layer because they
consume these lipoproteins in an attempt
at least assumed to eliminate the
growing lipoprotein burden however they
then turn into foam cells these are
immune cells that are overladen with
these lipoproteins and end up
dysfunctional cells these dysfunctional
cells recruit more immune cells but but
they also die creating a necrotic core
discussed earlier anyway exercise seems
to reinvigorate these lipoprotein burden
immune cells to migrate back out of the
aoma in addition exercise can reduce the
lipoprotein burden thereby reducing the
uptake of these lipoproteins into the
subendothelium in addition exercise
affects other lipoprotein types called
HDL HDL or highdensity lipoproteins are
not bound to these proteoglycans because
they do not contain the APO section that
is chemically attracted to the
proteoglycans however hdls have the
capacity to pick up cholesterol
molecules stuck inside the cells and
inside the apob containing lipoproteins
through a number of transport mechanisms
in doing so they can ux or liberate
colesterol molecules from the aoma and
return it to the liver to be excreted
this is called reverse cholesterol
transport so that's three ways by which
exercise reduces the size of the plaque
the aoma I'm sure there are some complex
signaling processes that are the driving
force for all that happening but I'd
like to get into some of the non-plaque
related ways that exercise can also help
prevent you from tasting the corroded
lips of death we're still leaning on
this review and therein it's pointed out
that exercise can also
cize blood vessels I'll straight up tell
you that I had no idea what that meant
but fortunately with my Superior 10 IQ
intellect I was able to manage to look
it up and learn about it so that I could
pretend like I knew all along right here
for you
collateralized blood vessels are blood
vessels that can become active when the
main blood vessel is incapable of
transporting nutrients and oxygen as
necessary essentially exercise promotes
the process of angiogenesis a word that
I have heard before wherein your body
produces more blood vessels in doing so
these blood vessels can attach
Downstream from the occlusion or near
occlusion therefore creating a natural
nonsurgical installed bypass which is
honestly really freaking cool what
fascinating is that the triggers of this
uh bypass formation are a esema or the
lack of blood flow but also be the way
that the fluid rubs across the atheroma
and the surrounding region apparently
that stimulates the blood vessel to
start sprouting a new blood flow system
that is
crazy in fact that process is so
efficient that some people no longer
feel chest L pains when they previously
did from the original aoma growing but
there's something else that exercise
does that's seldom discussed but we'll
get into that first let's discuss the
clinical evidence from exercise
shrinking plaque and then I'd like to
get into some of the applicable
information okay there are a few
randomized control trials that have
looked into this unfortunately I covered
them both in the past and someone a
stute brought up that this one had some
major statistical mistakes which makes
the interpretation difficult yet if we
demote that study and focus on the other
there's some intriguing findings in that
study researchers are randomly assigned
people with cardiovascular disease to a
moderate continuous endurance training
or high-intensity interval training
these men and women performed the
exercise three times per week for 12
weeks and had their Exercise capacity
measured but more importantly for us
they measured arterial plaque as
well unfortunately most of the measures
did not indicate an improvement however
one measure the size of the necrotic
core that we discussed earlier was
reduced in both exercise groups in fact
although it isn't overly objective
here's an image of the artery of a
person measured on the left before
exercise and on the right after exercise
the more red the more necrotic core and
the more green the more fibrous tissue
something that we haven't discussed yet
but we will because it's linked to this
additional benefit of exercise now the
less statistically rigorous study had
more impressive results but I wouldn't
feel comfortable adding that data here
because it may be because of their
statistical mistakes that they had more
impressive results however in the
scientific review that we went over they
reference a few other studies of varying
quality so I would like to see more
concrete data but across mechanisms and
some clinical data exercise does seem to
reduce plaque now how do we go about
erasing plaque from Our arteries well as
we discussed both a moderate intensity
urance training and a higher intensity
training led to plaque improvements
however the review mentions that a
Target to aim for is to burn 2200
calories per week equivalent to about 5
to six hours of exercise per week what
they also point out is that exercise
alone may be insufficient or at least it
may not produce the potent effect unless
paired with other factors especially one
reducing the number of apob containing
lipoproteins in the blood and two Poss
posibly reductions in blood pressure as
well both can be achieved through
nutrition weight loss or drugs what I
also noticed is that there's an exercise
protocol that keeps being brought up
across multiple studies and seems to
have the most robust effects in
improving heart health including plaque
reversal I've put together that
step-by-step protocol for the physionic
Insiders if you're interested it's
linked in the description and you get a
host of other benefits now there's
something else that exercise does to
your plaque but it's a bit nuanced
according to another review the
researchers point out that there's some
mixture in the studies in reference to
the effect exercise has on plaque
stability that means that we aren't just
concerned about the plaque being present
but also how it is present is it a
stable plaque or unstable unstable
plaque means that the top section the
most protruding section of the a Aroma
is capped by a thin fibrotic cap
essentially cells lay down collagen and
other proteins on top of the cholesterol
the immune cells lipoprotein mixture and
try to make sure that it doesn't break
off from the sheer stress of blood
pressure rubbing against it every moment
of the day if the top breaks off it
creates a blood clot that can olude a
downstream blood vessel so having a thin
fibrotic cap is unstable and ready to be
ripped off to create a blood clot
however a thick fibrous cap or a
calcified cap could stabilize the aoma
so that while it might still exist it
won't break into a
clot interestingly there's some evidence
that exercise can increase the
calcification of plaque measured via a
coronary artery calcification score a
CAC score however that evidence is a bit
all over the place with some studies
indicating otherwise for example in
athletes people who exercise a lot the
dark blue bars represent their plaque
makeup clearly there's more calcified
plaque but less mixed plaque which is
the most volatile and dangerous
according to the researchers to be clear
this is not set in stone so there's room
for more data just like everything
related to this subject still the
researchers included that the net is a
benefit of exercise through likely
plaque stabilization but also some other
mechanisms that we didn't even have time
to discuss here so the takeaway here is
that there's a mixed quality evidence
that exercise reverses plaque but the
evidence tentatively points to it being
possible through a number of mechanisms
I do think some other conditions need to
be met for the best effects like working
on reducing in blood pressure and apob
burden but the exercise also provides
unique ways of protecting against plaque
induced problems even aside from the
shrinking of the plaque itself in fact
one more way that exercise improves
heart health is by giving many heart
attacks no I am not joking it's called
cardiac preconditioning explained in
this next video or you might be more
interested did in some of my other work
right here thanks for watching
[Music]